Guide to the Carl F. Schreiber Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Carl F. Schreiber papers
1910-1957
YCGL MSS 22
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
5.5
(14 boxes)
The Carl F. Schreiber Papers consist of material generated by Schreiber as curator of the William A. Speck Collection at the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library and as a Yale faculty member. The bulk of the papers were left in the library when Schreiber retired; some material has been brought to the library by the Yale German Department and by occupants of the Palmer Schreiber Library in Bingham Tower. Material includes personal papers, correspondence, writing and research files, and writings by others, documenting Schreiber's research and curatorial activities which largely focused on the German authors Harro Harring and Goethe.
Schreiber, Carl F. (Carl Frederick), 1886-1960
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Bequest of Carl F. Schreiber, 1960.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Carl Frederick Schreiber (1886-1960)
Carl F. Schreiber was born in Saginaw, Michigan. His father, Hugo Friedrich, was a merchant; his mother was Adelaide Rueter. Schreiber received his B.A. from the University of Michigan in 1907, his M.A. from New York University in 1910, and his Ph.D. from Yale University in 1914. His dissertation, which remained unpublished, was entitled "Harro Harring: ein Beitrag zur Demagogenliteratur." After teaching German at an Illinois high school and at New York University, Schreiber came to Yale in 1909 as an instructor. By 1926 he had been promoted to full professor, and in 1928 he succeeded William A. Speck as curator of the William A. Speck Collection of Goetheana. In 1936 he was named the Leavenworth Professor of German Languages & Literatures. He retired from his faculty position in 1954 but stayed on as curator until his death.
Scope and Contents
The Carl F. Schreiber Papers consist of material generated by Schreiber as curator of the William A. Speck Collection at the Beinecke Rare Book & Manuscript Library and as a Yale faculty member. The bulk of the papers were left in the library when Schreiber retired; some material has been brought to the library by the Yale German Department and by occupants of the Palmer Schreiber Library in Bingham Tower. Material includes personal papers, correspondence, writing and research files, and writings by others, documenting Schreiber's research and curatorial activities which largely focused on the German authors Harro Harring and Goethe.
Schreiber's general professional correspondence is contained in the office correspondence of the Yale Collection of German Literature, where beginning in the 1940s it was interfiled with letters by Curt von Faber du Faur and Hedwig S. Dejon. Only letters strictly connected with specific projects and his correspondence relating to his research on Harro Harring and on Edgar Allan Poe have been classed here with his papers.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into three series: I. Personal and family papers, circa 1912-1935. II. Writings and research projects, circa 1910-1957. III. Writings by others, circa 1930s.
Authors, German; German literature -- 18th century; German literature -- 19th century; Goethe, Johann Wolfgang von, 1749-1832; Harring, Harro, 1798-1870; Schreiber, Carl F. (Carl Frederick), 1886-1960; Yale University -- Faculty
- Personal and family papers, circa 1912-1935; Series I; (2 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Included are primarily scrapbooks and files relating to Schreiber's trips to Germany.
  The scrapbooks contain newspaper clippings pasted in three columns per page. The clippings, dating from the 1890s, principally in German, some in English, are pasted on the pages of used ledger books of the 1870s from a business involving some sort of metered commodity. The prevalence of women's topics in the religion and poetry volumes suggests that the scrapbooks may have been compiled by a woman, possibly Schreiber's mother. A religious poem entitled "Take some part" near the end of the poetry volume is inscribed "Carl's recitative 1900."
  The files documenting Schreiber's trips to Germany in the 1930s contain a variety of travel-related correspondence, programs, invitations, and post cards. In 1931 he appears to have carried the Speck Collection items illustrated in the Speck portfolio of 1932 and catalog of 1940 to Germany, where the facsimiles were produced. In 1932 (the centenary of Goethe's death) he gave a radio speech in Germany. The 1934 trip was a tour sponsored by the Carl Schurz Foundation for American educators and students. Schreiber's wife and daughter accompanied him in 1935.
  - Scrapbook: Music (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook: Religion (Box 2)
  - Scrapbook: History (Box 2)
  - Scrapbook: Poems (Box 2)
  - School notebook entitled "Myths" (Box 2)
    This material also contains Latin translation excercises and poetry.
  - "Yale Library Associates - Schreiber Memorial Fund" (Box 2)
  - Frachtbrief. Bavarian railroad form tracing the shipment of Schreiber's luggage, 1912 August (Box 2)
    Carl F. Schreiber was a traveling fellow at the Uniersity of Munich from 1911 to 1912..
  - AL (partial draft) to Russell H. Chittenden, New York, accepting employment at Yale., 1913 March 9 (Box 2)
    This letter was found in a dictionary once used in the Speck Collection office.
  - Trip to Germany, 1931 (Box 2)
  - Trip to Germany, 1932 (Box 2)
  - Trip to Germany, 1934 (Box 2)
  - Trip to Germany, 1935 (Box 2)
  - Obituaries (Box 2)
  - Photographic portrait (Box 2)
  - German student fraternity dueling sword
- Writings and research projects, circa 1910-1957; Series II; (10 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged into ten subseries: Lectures and speeches; Reviews; Writings on German literature; Harro Harring: research materials, correspondence, thesis; Fiction and Fantasty; Speck portfolio; Minimum German; Speck catalog, 1940; The "Chicago" Goethe; and Edgar Allen Poe.
  While Schreiber's doctoral research was on Harro Harring (1798-1870), he never published his dissertation on this radical writer and political agitator. His scholarly career and writing were instead devoted largely to Goethe, reflecting his association with the Speck Collection for some three decades.
  Schreiber's research materials on Harro Harring are described in more detail than the rest of the papers. This section was described earlier for the information of the late Thomas Thode, whose Harring bibliography appeared in 2005.
  As curator of the Speck Collection, Schreiber was deeply involved in two of its major publications, Goetheana. A centenary portfolio of forty-three facsimiles and reproductions of unique or rare items from the William A Speck Collection of Goetheana, and Goethe's works with the exception of Faust: A catalogue compiled by members of the Yale University Library staff, published by the Yale University Press in 1932 and 1940 respectively. The latter, conceived along the lines of the Katalog der Sammlung Kppenberg (2nd edition, Leipzig: Insel, 1928), was intended as a four-volume set, but no more was ever issued. (Volume 2 was to have described the collection's Faust holdings; volume 3 was to have contained biographical material about Goethe; and volume 4 was to have brought addenda and a much-needed index.)
  The publishing history of the Portfolio and the Catalogue are bound together by the facsimiles contained in each. In 1931, Schreiber carried 43 items from the Speck Collection to Germany, where facsimiles were made by Albrecht Frisch, a printer in Berlin who specialized in photoengraving and who had worked on the catalog of the Kippenberg Collection. The facsimiles were produced in sets of 1,000 copies each. Five-hundred from each set were issued as the Portfolio in 1932; eight years later, the other 500 copies of seventeen of the facsimiles were bound into the first volume of the Catalogue. The other 26 sets of facsimiles have been preserved for years, and although the paper is now brittle and unsuitable to be bound in any book, the curator resisted various attempts to discard the remaining facsimiles. (She has distributed some of them in various ways as pertinent occasions arose, so most sets are incomplete.) Sets of the Frisch facsimiles in various formats are preserved in the Schreiber papers, along with correspondence about their production.
  Also scheduled for publication in the centenary year 1932 was a proposed two-volume essay collection called "Goethe in America." In the mid-1920s Schreiber and his Yale colleague Adolph B. Benson began to collect papers and prepare them for publication, but in the end funds to print the book could not be raised. Seventeen papers are present in the collection, some of them by major scholars of the time, along with a file of correspondence, plans, and outlines.
  Another scholarly project that came to naught was the so-called "Chicago" (later "Yale") Goethe. The history and background of this initiative is outlined in a letter from Victor Lange to Heinz Blum, dated 29 March 1954 in Box 10. In 1948, a group of scholars (Schreiber, Victor Lange, Arnold E. Bergraesser), anticipating the bicentennial of Goethe's birth, entered negotiations with the University of Chicago Press to publish a 4-volume edition of Goethe's works in new English translations. After some difficulties, documented in the collection by the example of Schreiber's translation of Goethe's Novelle, the University of Chicago Press transferred its contracts to the Henry Regnery Company, then also in Chicago; that contract is dated 1952. The arrangement with Henry Regnery apparently failed, and in 1954 Heinz Blum, chairman of the Yale German Department, attempted to revive the project as the "Yale" Goethe, to be published in 12 volumes by the Yale University Press. Financial subvention was promised by Frederick von Schleinitz, and the project seemed to be getting underway (without Schreiber's collaboration, however), but the documentation ends abruptly in 1957 and no volumes of "Yale" Goethe were ever published.
  Materials in the Schreiber papers, although fragmentary, show that the translation of Dichtung und Wahrheit was well underway in the late 1940s: Minna Steel Smith's English version (London, 1908), itself based on the Oxenford/Morrison translation of 1849, was typed out in several copies and used as a basic text. Schreiber and his collaborators, Wallace J. Williamson and Jane Bannard Greene, made revisions. A version conflated from their various changes was being retyped and submitted to the University of Chicago Press. Not all copies for all sections of the book are preserved, but the typescripts present for Book XIII illustrate the working process. The Götz translation may belong to the Yale phase of the project; that play is not listed in the University of Chicago Press contracts.
  Schreiber's interest in Edgar Allan Poe dates to the summer of 1925, when he went to New York City to examine Superior Court records. While looking for documents relating to a suit that Harro Harring had brought against Harper and Brothers in 1846 (Harring, it will be remembered, was the subject of Schreiber's dissertation), he found instead the records of Poe's suit against the owners of the New York Evening Mirror, documents previously unknown to Poe scholars. Around this time Schreiber made Poe the focus of his personal book collecting: he set out to gather every book of which Poe had published a review, some 240 titles. Schreiber published at least two substantial articles about Poe: "A close-up of Poe" in The Saturday Review of Literature for 9 October 1926, and "Mr. Poe at his conjurations again" the The Colophon, 1930. The Schreiber papers retain other Poe materials, including Schreiber's essay "Poe and Goethe," which is related textually to "Mr. Poe at his conjurations again." Schreiber seems also to have devoted a good deal of research to prove Poe's role in the compilation of The Laws of Etiquette (Philadephia: Carey, Lea, and Blanchard, 1836) and on an essay called "The Canon of Good Breeding."
  A small convolute of typed transcriptions concerning the composer Robert Lucas Pearsall from well-known periodicals and reference books was discarded; Schreiber's interest in Pearsall may have been due to the fact that Pearsall made an attempt to translate Faust.
  - Lectures and speeches
    - Assorted correspondence about planned lectures, circa 1931/2 (Box 3)
    - Weimar. "Goethe in Amerika." Typescripts, autograph, printed version (Jb. der Goethe Gesellschaft, 18), 1932 (Box 3)
    - Berlin. "Goethes Bedeutung für das Geistesleben der Gegenwart," radio broadcast for Reichs Rundfunk Gesellschaft. Typescript, English, with related correspondence, 1932 (Box 3)
    - Introduction of lecturer: Friedrich von der Leyen, 1932 (Box 3)
    - Introductory Remarks. Goethe Group (with correspondence, an MLA section), 1932 (Box 3)
    - "Neues ueber den Erstdruck von Goethes Faust", typescripts and autograph, 1934 January 30 (Box 3)
    - Weimar. 50th Anniversary of the Goethe Gesellschaft. Typescript, German., 1935 August 28 (Box 3)
    - Hartford. [German culture]. Typescript and autograph. English., 1936 (Box 3)
    - "The Meaning of Goethe." Typscript, 1949 (Box 3)
    - Stanford University. "Goethe 1932-1949." Typescript and autograph, English. (Box 3)
      This address was also given at the Modern Language Association in 1949.
    - "America celebrates Goethe's 200th anniversary," Yale news Bureau radio broadcast, WTIC. Typescript and autograph., 1949 March 20 (Box 3)
    - Yale. Introduction of lecturer: Barker Fairley, 1949 March 22 (Box 3)
    - "Lecture on the Collection of Goetheana" ("Goethe lecture with slides") (Box 3)
    - "Goethe - A Tribute." Typescript, English (Box 3)
  - Reviews (Box 3)
  - Writings on German literature
    - "Coleridge to Boosey - Boosey to Coleridge," YULG, 1948 (Box 4)
    - "Einiges," Monatshefte, 1943 (Box 4)
    - "Fiekchen oder der zerschlagene Schlitten.", 1944? (Box 4)
      This is a rebuttal to an article by Thomas K. Brown, Jr., though authorship is uncertain.
    - "The German and his romanticism", 1927 (Box 4)
      This is from the anthology Fiction and fantasy of German romance.
    - "Goethe 1932 - Ein Aufruf," Monatshefte (Box 4)
    - "German at Yale," American-German Review, 1935 (Box 4)
    - Goethe—Herrnhut—America. Jb. der deutsch-amerikanischen historischen Gesellschaft von Illinois, 1920-21 (Box 4)
    - "Goethe on Weltliteratur," privately printed, 1923 (Box 4)
    - [Goethe year] Program for the Goethe year., 1932? (Box 4)
    - [Hauptmann] "Gerhart Hauptmann" (Box 4)
    - [Heine] "A lost portrait of Heine, found", "A second profile of the young Heine found" (Box 4)
    - "Irreducible minimum of German.", 1932 September (Box 4)
    - [Kippenberg] Tribute to Anton Kippenberg, 1937? (Box 4)
    - [Malthus] "Daniel Malthus: Translator of the 'Sorrows of Werter'" (Box 4)
    - "Mittler—Jung-Stilling. Ein Vorbild zu den 'Wahlverwandtschaften,'" Archiv für das Studium der neueren Sprachen und Literaturen, 1924 (Box 4)
    - [Raphael] Introduction to Alice Raphael's Faust translation: Limited Editions Club, 1932. "A note on Faust translations." 1930., circa 1930-1932 (Box 4)
      Published in conjunction with the Jonathan Cape edition of the Raphael translation. With related correspondence
    - "Die schöne Seele" (Box 4)
    - [Speck Collection] "The William A. Speck Collection of Goethiana." 1916 (Collections of Yale University, 3) "The William A. Speck Collection of Goetheana." 1931 "The William A. Speck Collection of Goetheana." Undated, circa 1916-1931 (Box 4)
    - [Werfel] "The pure in heart." On Franz Werfel's novel Barbara, oder die Frömmigkeit, 1929, published in English in 1931 as The pure in heart (Box 4)
    - "Who is my neighbor?" Editorial, German-American Review, 1936 (Box 4)
    - "William Alfred Speck." Various drafts of the biography that appeared in Goethe's works with the exception of Faust. A catalogue... (1940), 2 (Box 4)
    - "Zur Vorgeschichte des Faust-Fragmentdrucks" (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous printed items not represented in Orbis (Box 4)
  - Harro Harring: research materials, correspondence, thesis.
    The second American hand mentioned in this section is largely the same one.
    - Harro Harring: writings
      - "Aphorismen" (Box 5)
        Contained within this folder are typed excerpts from a longer work with numbered sections up to at least 108, 4 leaves. In the same folder: "Nachträge zu Heine's Reisebildern," with the imprint information Hoffmann und Campe, 1831, and the note "Harring's Erstling in Gebiete der Recension!" 5 leaves.
      - Briefe über die Vereinigten Staaten Nordamerikas, in Bezug auf ihr Verhältnis zur Europäischen Revolution und zum Kampfe im Orient, 1854. Transcript in the hand of Johann Sass, 131 numbered leaves., 4 (Box 5)
      - Blüthen. Vermischte Gedichte (1825). Excerpts, typed and in Schreiber's hand, 8 leaves. (Box 5)
        In the same folder, another group of poems, apparently drawn from several sources, typed and in Schreiber's hand and another American hand. 14 leaves.
      - Blutstrophen. Deutsche Gedichte (1832). Typed transcript, 17 leaves with some marginal notes in Schreiber's hand. (Box 5)
        In the same folder, other poems: Es ist kein Traum. Handwritten transcript, 3 p.; An Mazzini. Transcript in Schreiber's hand, 4 p.; Nimmer nach Amerika. Transcript in Schreiber's hand, 2 p.; Der Völkerfreund. Transcript in Schreiber's hand, 3 p.; Der Bundestag. Transcript inSchreiber's hand, 1 p.; Mein Vaterland! Transcript in Schreiber's hand, 2 p.; Das Bild der Rose. Typed transcript with marginalia by Schreiber, 2 p.; "Politische Lieder aus dem 2. Stück "Das Volk." Typed transcript with a few marginalia by Schreiber, 5 p. (excerpts? Indications of: Seite 142, 161, 194, 233, 235).
      - Deutschland. Excerpts from the newspaper, many dated 1831-32, some typed, most in Schreiber's hand, 18 leaves (Box 5)
      - Es ist kein Traum! (later title of the poem written for the "Hambacher Fest" of May 1832). Notes and transcripts in Schreiber's hand and another American hand, 6 leaves. With two photostats identified as "Hambacher Fest, Pictures." (Box 5)
      - Faust im Gewande der Zeit (1831). Reading notes and remarks in Schreiber's hand, 4 leaves; typed transcript of the beginning of the publication, 2 leaves. (Box 5)
      - The Funeral of Goethe. From the German of Harro Harring. Translation by Alexamder H. Everett (Democratic Review, Nov. 1842). Translation of the poem "Göthe" in Die Möwe (See Thode, p. 101). Typed transcript, 6 p. (XV stanzas); handwritten copy of German (American hand). (Box 5)
      - Gedanken über Wahrheit (1832). Typed transcription, 10 numbered leaves. In the same folder, notes and excerpts from Worte eines Menschen. Dem Gläubigen von La Mennais gewidmet (1834), in Schreiber's hand, continued in another American hand, 2 leaves. (Box 5)
      - Mémoires sur la Jeune Italie et sur les dernier événemens de Savoie (1834). Transcript in the hand of Schreiber (through page 108). Ends "Harro Harring, Le 27 juillet 1834," 18 leaves., 2 (Box 5)
        These folders contain the following related materials: An excerpt headed: "General Dufour" in der Savoyer Putsch von 1834. Von Prof. Dr. Alfred Stern," in Schreiber's hand, 4 leaves.; Proclamation. Soldats! Soldati! Savoy, 31 Jan. 1834. Broadside in French and Italian. Photostat from the Haus-Hof-und-Staats-Archiv, Wien.
      - "Mitteilungen über Russland. Von Harro Harring. N Y. Criminal Zeitung." Typed transcript with title (on the wrapper) in Johann Sass's hand, 34 numbered pages. (Box 5)
      - "Die Möwe... Neu aufgelegt von mehreren Deutschen" (1840). Transcription of title page and preface by J Garnier, in another American hand, 2 leaves. Transcription of poems "Die Möwe" and "Navarino" in Schreiber's hand, 2 leaves. Transcription of a review of the book (Schlsewig. Holst. Blätter) in Schreiber's hand, 1 leaf. (Box 5)
      - "Notizen zum Verzeichnis meiner sämmtlichen Schriften. Für Oscar Falke, Louis Fricker, Theodor Remi etc." Transcription in the hand of Johann Sass, 5 double leaves. (Box 5)
        The copy is evidently made from a manuscript: several places are marked "unleserlich."
      - "Der Renegat auf Morea." (1831). Excerpts in Schreiber's hand, 6 leaves, with 2 leaves of notes, one of them in Schreiber's hand. (Box 5)
        In the same folder, notes and transcripts relating to Die Mainotten (1825) and Der Corsar (1825), 9 leaves. The folder is labeled "Philhellener-Drama."
      - "Die Schwarzen von Giessen" (1831). Partial transcription, mostly in Schreiber's hand, some passages in the other American hand, 23 leaves. (Box 5)
      - "Skizze aus London" (1838). Transcriptions, typed, in Schreiber's hand and in the other American hand, 15 leaves. (Box 5)
      - "La Telyn (Harpe) d'un Scandinave" (1839). Excerpts in Schreiber's hand, 4 leaves. (Box 5)
      - "Die Völker" (1832). Excerpt in Schreiber's hand, 5 leaves. (Box 5)
      - "Das Volk. Dramatische Szenen zur Darstellung durch Volksfreunde" (1832). Transcription, partly typed, partly handwritten, mostly by Schreiber, some passages in another American hand, ca. 72 leaves. (Box 5)
        In the same folder, partial typed transcription of the poem "Peter Wisozki, der edle Pole" (1832), 1 leaf.
      - "Vorläufer des Rhonghar Jarr" (1828). Excerpt, "Serenaden und Phantasien [eines friesischen Sängers]" in Schreiber's hand, 3 leaves; with a transcribed review, 1830, in another American hand, 1 leaf. (Box 5)
    - Harro Harring: letters
      - ":Originals" - ALS to "Lieber Freund." Schestedt bei Rendsburg. 19 April 1849, 7 pages on two folded leaves (original). With ALS to "Lieber Bruder." Kiel, 1 August 1821 (photostat), and a manuscript poem titled "Schiller's Triumph in Leipzig, signed Adlph Böttger, with a presentation inscription dated 1927 to Schreiber from his grandfather. (Box 5)
      - "Briefe an Johanna Mesdorf (Später Direktor des Museums Vaterländischer Altertümer in Kiel," 1848-1853. Handwritten transcription, 34 numbered pages (Box 5)
        This material is in the same paper as Sass transcripts below, but not in his hand.
      - "Briefe an Todsen." 1821-43. Transcriptions., 9 (Box 5)
        Leaves numbered 1-257 and 1-105 in a hand resembling J. Sass's; 1-66 in a different (German) hand. Another set of transcripts, typed, 1833-38; these appear to be letters not represented in the handwritten transcript.
      - "Briefe an Todsen." 1821-43. Transcriptions., 2 (Box 6)
      - Transcripts of letters by Harring then owned by Johann Sass. In Sass's hand, with a covering letter from him, Berlin, 12 April 1928. 27 single and double leaves, each representing one letter., circa 1928 (Box 6)
      - Convolute of letters by and to Harring, including correspondence with his brother, with Todsen, to "Justizrat von Starkenburg [reading of St and k doubtful]. Handwritten transcriptions. (Box 6)
    - Harro Harring: documentary materials
      - "Briefe von Harro Harring, oder am Harro H., wie sie in den periodischen Berichten der Polizei-Notizen zu finden sind (1852)." Typed transcripts with titles and annotations in the hand of Johann Sass(?), 20 leaves. (Box 6)
      - Notes concerning Harring's activities in 1835 and a poem entitled "Lied der Liebe," also dated 1835. Typed transcripts, annotated in Sass's (?) hand. (Box 6)
      - "Notes from Geheimes Staatsarchiv, Berlin-Dahlem." Transcripts, mostly in Schreiber's hand, 59 half leaves. (Box 6)
        This folder also contains a TLS from M. Klinkenberg (Geheimes Staats-Archiv) to Schreiber, Berlin-Dahlem, 13 April 1928, 1 leaf, concerning arrangements for Schreiber to work in archives in Vienna.
      - "Schäfer, Berichte aus Paris, after returning from London 26 Nov. 1838 and 6 Dez. 1839 [folder title]." (Box 6)